A Finding Aid to the Forbes Watson Papers, 1840-1967, bulk 1900-1960, in the Archives of American Art AAA.watsforb
Archives of American Art
- Artist/Patron Files, 1840-1967; Series 6; (Box 6-9, 15, OV 21; 2.8 linear feet)
  - Oversized Oil Painting by Unidentified Artist, undated; (from Box 6, Folder 50) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Photographs of Aaron Bohrod and His Work, undated; (from Box 6, Folder 70) (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Photographs of Art Work by Howard Cook, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 4) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Photograph of Juliana Force, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 42) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Photographs of Art Work by Mordecai Gorelik, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 56) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Photograph of Art Work by William Gropper, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 59) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Photograph of Art Work by Edwin Booth Grossman, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 60) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Photograph of Art Work by George Harding, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 62) (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Lithograph by George "Pop" Hart, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 63) (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Photographs of Art Work by George Kratina, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 92) (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Photograph of Art Work by Fred Dana Marsh, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 124) (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Photographs of John Sloan, undated; (from Box 8, Folder 55) (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Photograph of Ralph Stackpole, undated; (from Box 8, Folder 61) (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Photographs of Art Work by Maurice Sterne, undated; (from Box 8, Folder 65) (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Photograph of Art Work by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, undated; (from Box 9, Folder 6) (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Photograph of William Zorach, undated; (from Box 9, Folder 11) (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Lithograph by Glenn O. Coleman, undated; (from Box 6, Folder 95) (Box OV 21)
  - Oversized Photographs of Art Work by John Holmer, undated; (from Box 7, Folder 69) (Box OV 21)
  - Oversized Drawing by Symeon Shimin, undated; (from Box 8, Folder 51) (Box OV 21)
- Art and Architecture File, 1929-1930; Series 7; (Box 9; 35 folders)
  The Art and Architecture File consists of reference files of photographs and notes concerning miscellaneous unattributed art works, American architecture, and furnishings.
  - Folk Art Sculpture, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
  - Miscellaneous Sculpture, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Portrait Paintings of Women, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Portrait Paintings of Men, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Paintings of Children and Families, undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 17-18)
  - Miscellaneous Marine Paintings, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Paintings of Landscapes and Still Life Images, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Buildings in California, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Addison Gallery of Art, Andover, Massachusetts, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Buildings in New York City, 1929, undated; (7 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 16) (Box 9, Folder 23-29)
  - Art Work from the Brooklyn-Paramount Theatre, Brooklyn, New York, undated (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Buildings in New York State, 1930, undated; (3 folders) (Box 9, Folder 31-33)
  - Buildings in Washington, D.C., undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 34-35)
  - Miscellaneous Buildings, undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Historic Interiors at Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, undated; (5 folders) (Box 9, Folder 37-41)
  - Historic Interiors at Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, undated (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Historic Interiors, undated (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous Furnishings, undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 44-45)
  - Miscellaneous Art Work, undated (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - Oversized Photograph of Façade of the U. S. Assay Office at Metropolitan Museum of Art, undated; (from Box 9, Folder 23) (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Notes and Writings, 1875-1950; Series 8; (Box 9-10; 1.2 linear feet)
  Notes and writings consist of miscellaneous notes and typescripts of lectures and published articles not directly related to Watson's work for the U. S. Treasury Department. There is also a set of notebook pages containing a list of articles, miscellaneous notes and typescripts.
  - Notebook Pages, 1940-1946; (9 folders) (Box 9, Folder 47-55)
  - Lists, 1929-1930, undated (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Manuscript Fragments, undated (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Typescript Fragments, undated (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Typescript "1913-1923" Concerning the Armory Show, undated (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Radio Talk Typescripts Ghost-Written by Forbes Watson for Others, undated (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Typescripts of Lectures 3-5, undated (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - "The American Artist's Opportunity,", undated (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Speech Delivered to American Society of Painters, Gravers, and Sculptors, undated (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Art Students League Lecture No. 1, undated (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Lecture for Cedar Rapids, undated (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Lecture on Prints for Cleveland, undated (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Columbia Lecture No. 2, undated (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art Talks, undated (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - "The Accepted Thing, the New Vision, a Curious Animosity, the Enemies of Art,", undated (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - "The Aftermath of Modernism,", undated (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - "Art in the New America,", undated (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - "The Background of Present-Day Painting, undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 72-73)
  - "Evasion and Stylization,", undated (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - "Cezanne,", undated (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - "Civilized Contemporary Painting,", undated (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - "Communism's Gift to the United States,", undated (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - "Contemporary Portraits,", undated (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - "The Cost of a Painting,", undated (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - "Eighteenth Century Europe,", undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 80-81)
  - Concerning Exhibition of American Art, undated (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - "Exhibitions Coming and Going,", undated (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - "Flemish, Dutch, and Spanish Art,", undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 84-85)
  - "Free Exhibitions,", undated (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - "From Walk-Up to the Land,", undated (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - "Gothic,", undated (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - "Greek Art,", undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 89-90)
  - "The Home Product,", undated (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - "How the Artist Feels about It,", undated (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - "Hustling 'Em Off the Stage,", undated (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - "In at the Birth,", undated (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Concerning Independents, undated (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - "Is There an American Art?,", undated (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - "The Material Uses of the Fake,", undated (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - "Henri Matisse", undated (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - "Modern Trends in Art,", undated (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - "National Character in American Art,", undated (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - "Opportunities in the Arts,", undated (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - "Parisian Taste in America,", undated (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - "The Power of Modesty,", undated (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - "Regionalism,", undated (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - "Religion in Art,", undated (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - "Renaissance 2,", undated (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - "The Role of the Subject in Painting,", undated (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - "Roman and Byzantine Art,", undated (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - "The Significance of Modern Painting,", undated (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - "Social Consciousness Returns to Art,", undated (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Concerning Maurice Sterne, undated (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - "Twenty-Five Years Ago,", undated (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - "Two Realities,", undated (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - "Uncommissioned Portraits,", undated (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - "The Word Modern,", undated (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - "The World of Art,", undated (Box 9, Folder 116)
  - "Lectures Held at Art Students League of New York,", 1924 (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Concerning Early American Murals, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 118)
  - "The Root of Art,", 1929 (Box 9, Folder 119)
  - "The Blessings of the Crash,", 1929-1930 (Box 9, Folder 120)
  - Concerning the Society of Independent Artists, Inc., 1931 (Box 9, Folder 121)
  - "Miss Lizzie Bliss,", 1931 (Box 9, Folder 122)
  - "Whitney Museum Talk,", 1931 (Box 9, Folder 123)
  - Concerning Exhibition of Society of Independent Artists, Inc., 1932 (Box 9, Folder 124)
  - "Dali and Rockwell,", 1933 (Box 9, Folder 125)
  - Typescript Fragment, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 126)
  - "The American Scene,", 1934 (Box 9, Folder 127)
  - "The People and Their Art,", 1935 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Egyptian Art,", 1936 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "The Fate of Unheralded Acts,", 1936 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Art Teachers' Lecture at Howard University, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Bibliography of American Painting,", 1937 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "The Pattern of Our Period,", 1937; (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 6-8)
  - "What With One Fair and Another,", 1939 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Report "Community Arts Program,", 1939 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - "God Bless America,", 1940 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - "Serious Joys,", 1940 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Lecture at Art Students League, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Lecture for Washington Dance Association at the Phillips Gallery, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - "The Benefit of Great Art,", 1941 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Book Review of Winslow Homer by Lloyd Goodrich, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - "Interview with Colonel Kemper at the Pentagon,", 1944 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - "George Bellows: the Boy Wonder of American Painting,", 1945 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Radio Talk by Forbes Watson and Nancy Osgood, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - "Museum Public Relations,", 1946 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - "Incidents - No. 2,", 1946 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - "The Artist's Position in the Community,", 1946 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - "Art Lectures,", 1946 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - "The Picture That Mr. Widener Liked,", 1947 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Art Students League Talks 2, 3, 5, and 6 Concerning 19th Century American Painting, 1947; (4 folders) (Box 10, Folder 25-28)
  - "Kuniyoshi,", 1948 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - "Painters, Sculptors, and Public,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 1 "Popes, Princes, and Public,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 2 "Feathers and Wings,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Art Students League Talk (No. 2) "El Greco, Velasquez, and Goya,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 3 "Portraits Commissioned and Uncommissioned,", 1949; (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 34-35)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 4 "The Artist's Education, Etc.,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 5 "The Museum and the Artist,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 6 "The Achievement of Two Ladies,", 1949; (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 38-39)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 7 "The Army and Art,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Art Students League Talk (No. 7) "What the Public Buys,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 9 "Art on the Wall?Master or Servant?,", 1949; (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 42-43)
  - Art Students League Talk No. 10 "Publicity, the Modern Monster,", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - "American Painting 1750 to 1950," (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Metropolitan Museum Talks 1, 2, and 3 "Twentieth Century American Painting,", 1950; (8 folders) (Box 10, Folder 46-53)
  - "Part II (Reminiscences)" by Unidentified Author, undated (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - "Exploration of the Colorado River of the West and Its Tributaries?" by J. W. Powell, 1875 (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - "Sculpture and Americans" by Robert Cronbach, undated (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - "The Expositions in Paris" by Marc Debrol, undated (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - "Louis David: His Modern Appeal" by Alys M. Decker, undated (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - "The Third Dimension in Painting" by E. Dickson, undated (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - "Federal Character in Architecture" by Charles Goodman, undated (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - "Awards of the Mighty" by Guido, undated (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - "New Painters of sentiment and Mystery" by Henry Russell Hitchcock, Jr., undated (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - "A Note on H. E. Schnakenbert" by Mildred Palmer, undated (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - "Modernism in the Midwest" by Sam Putnam, undated (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - "Head in Natural Maine boulder," "In Affection," "Mother and Child," "The Reclining Cat," and "The Spirit of the Dance," by William Zorach, undated (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - "Random Notes" Possibly by Allen Tucker or Marget Sargent, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - "Zapotec Urns" by E. P. Richardson, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - "Notes on the Whitney Museum of American Art" by Eleanor Lambert, 1930-1931 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - "Do We Need A Museum of Modern Art?" by Unidentified Author, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - "Exhibition of Newer Super-Realism at the Morgan Memorial" by A. Everett Austin, Jr., 1931 (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - "The Modern Artist and the Modern World" by Frank Callcott, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 71)
- Scrapbooks, 1904-1951; Series 9; (Box 9, 11, 14, BV 18-20; 1.8 linear feet)
  Nine scrapbooks and loose scrapbook pages primarily contain miscellaneous clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs. The Whitney Studio Club Scrapbook contains clippings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, annotations about sales of art work, and a list of exhibitions during the 1928-1930 seasons. Scrapbook 4 contains clippings of Watson's articles for The Evening Post and Scrapbook 7 contains clippings of Watson's articles for The World newspaper.
  - Whitney Studio Club Scrapbook, 1924-1930 (Box 10, Folder 72)
  - Scrapbook Pages, 1913-1951; (4 folders) (Box 10, Folder 73-76)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1904-1943 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1912-1915 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1913-1916 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1922-1929 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook Pages, 1936-1937 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1928-1929 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1915-1933 (Box BV 18)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1923-1925 (Box BV 19)
  - Scrapbook 7, 1925-1927 (Box BV 20)
- Printed Material, 1900-1961; Series 10; (Box 10, 12-13, 16-17; 1.5 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of clippings, including copies of the Hue and Cry newspaper, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, calendars of events, brochures for the Art Students League, book catalogs, books The Art Spirit by Robert Henri, and Art Treasures and Intrigue by James Henry Duveen, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, undated; (2 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 16) (Box 10, Folder 77-78)
  - Clippings, 1900-1908; (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 79-81)
  - Clippings, 1914-1918; (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - Clippings, 1922-1929; (5 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 16) (Box 10, Folder 84-88)
  - Clippings, 1930-1939; (7 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 16) (Box 10, Folder 89-95)
  - Clippings, 1940-1949; (4 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 16) (Box 10, Folder 96-99)
  - Clippings, 1950-1953; (5 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 17) (Box 10, Folder 100-104)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1921-1949, undated; (7 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 17) (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
  - Prospectus from MacDowell Club of New York, 1914 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Prospectus for Competitive Print Exhibition at Print Club of Cleveland, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Calendars of Events, 1934-1945 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report of the Worcester Art Museum, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Brochures for the Art Students League, 1921-1924 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Book Catalogs, 1940-1942 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - The Art Spirit by Robert Henri, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Art Treasures and Intrigue by James Henry Duveen, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Advancing American Art with Text by Hugo Weisgall, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Galley Proof Sheets for Miscellaneous Publications, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1938-1961, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Clippings, undated; from Box 10, Folder 78 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Issues of the Hue and Cry Newspaper, 1929; from Box 10, Folder 88 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1939; from Box 10, Folder 95 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1940; from Box 10, Folder 96 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1941; from Box 10, Folder 97 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1942; from Box 10, Folder 98 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1943-1945; from Box 10, Folder 98 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1946-1947; from Box 10, Folder 99 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1948-1949; from Box 10, Folder 99 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1950; from Box 10, Folder 100 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1951; from Box 10, Folder 100 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1952; from Box 10, Folder 103 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalog for Whitney Studio Galleries, 1930; from Box 12, Folder 4 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1900-1950; Series 11; (Box 13; 6 folders)
  Photographs are of Forbes Watson, family members including his wife, painter Nan Watson, members of the Art Students League including Peggy Bacon, Minna Citron, Paul Juley, Stewart Klonis, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, and Reginald Marsh. There are also photographs of juries for the Carnegie Institute International Exhibitions that include colleagues Alfred H. Barr, Jr., Gifford Beal, Guy Pene DuBois, Leon Kroll, Henri Matisse, Homer Saint-Gaudens, and Maurice Sterne.
  - Forbes Watson, 1900-1950, undated; (3 folders) (Box 13, Folder 5-7)
  - Watson with Family and Friends, 1900-1950, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Watson at Art Students League, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Art Juries for Carnegie Institute International Exhibitions, 1929-1934, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)